Scott R. Sanders teaching and faculty files, 1971-2009 C359
Indiana University Archives
Scott R. Sanders teaching and faculty files
1971-2009
1989-2009
Indiana University Archives
Sanders, Scott R. (Scott Russell), 1945-
C359
4 cubic feet 4 boxes
Scott Russell Sanders taught in the Indiana University English Department from 1971-2009. He specialized in writing fiction, and also was heavily involved with the Wells Scholars program, serving as its director from 1997 to 2003. This collection consists of the teaching and faculty files of Dr. Sanders.
Access Restrictions
Information related to grades, student evaluations of classes, and recommendations are closed to researchers at this time.
Advance notice required for access to collection.
Biographical Note
Scott Russell Sanders was a Professor at Indiana University for the duration of his teaching career, 1971-2009. He demonstrated an interest in both literature and science, initially attending Brown University on a physics scholarship before his graduate study in literature at Cambridge. As a member of the IU's English department, he became recognized as one of the finest essayists in the country, releasing more than twenty books, both fiction and non-fiction, including the science fiction novel Terrarium and the collections Writing from the Center, In Limestone Country, and The Paradise of Bombs. Sanders also played a large role in the Wells Scholars program during his Indiana career, frequently teaching courses in the program and serving as the program director from 1997-2003. His writings and courses both demonstrate an interest in natural history in addition to focusing on more traditional literary subjects, such as in his Imagining Nature courses and publications such as his 2009 A Conservationist Manifesto.
Arrangement
The Scott R. Sanders papers are arranged in two series, Teaching files and Faculty files.
Scope and Content Note
The Scott R. Sanders papers are organized into two series. The first series, Teaching files, consists of the records created for classes taught by Sanders during his tenure at Indiana University. The individual folders are arranged chronologically by semester, and span the period from 1971 to 2009. The series includes handouts, teaching and lecture notes, as well as some of Sanders' correspondence with students and fellow faculty. For some of these files access is restricted because they contain sensitive or confidential information.
The second series, Faculty files, contains records created by or about Sanders during his Indiana University career. Included within this series are notifications about various awards that Sanders received during his career, promotional material about talks or recitations that he would deliver, correspondence, and his annual faculty summary reports. For some of these files access is restricted.
Additional papers of Dr. Sanders are housed at IU's Lilly Library. Consult Lilly staff for further information.
Separated Material
Three images removed and transferred to the Photograph Collection. One, a picture of a squirrel, was from the Spring 1990 Imagining Nature. The second was a picture of a humpback whale and was from the 1991 "Imagining Nature" IFS folder. The third picture was a group photograph of the 2003 Wells Scholars finalists, and was removed from the Spring 2004 H203 Life Stories folder.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2009/041.
Provenance
Transfer from Dr. Sanders, May 2009.
Appraisal
Duplicate copies of class handouts and of materials in the faculty files, as well as attendance and grade reports, were discarded.
Literature --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Authors --Archives.; Literature teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Sanders, Scott R. (Scott Russell), 1945- -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of English -- History -- Sources; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of English -- History -- Sources
- Teaching files, 1971-2009 (Box 1)
  - L411 Society in the novel, Fall 1971 (Box 1)
  - English L202 Literary Interp, Fall 1971 (Box 1)
  - L346 Modern British fiction, Spring 1972 (Box 1)
  - W303 Student writing workshop, Spring 1972 (Box 1)
  - W203 Writing workshop, Fall 1972 (Box 1)
  - L346, Fall 1972 (Box 1)
  - L142 Science fiction, Spring 1973 (Box 1)
  - L411 Marxism & literature with Sperber, Spring 1973 (Box 1)
  - W301 Writing fiction, Fall 1973 (Box 1)
  - L381 Recent writing with Paul Strohm, Fall 1973 (Box 1)
  - L142 Fictions, Spring 1974 (Box 1)
  - L374 Lit. of extreme situations, Spring 1974 (Box 1)
  - L649 British Lit. since 1900, Fall 1975 (Box 1)
  - W303 Poetry writing, Fall 1975 (Box 1)
  - L381 Science fiction, Spring 1976 (Box 1)
  - W103 Creative writing, Spring 1976 (Box 1)
  - English L354 American Lit, Fall 1976 (Box 1)
  - L381 Recent American fiction, Fall 1976 (Box 1)
  - W103 Intro to Creative Writing, Spring 1977 (Box 1)
  - English L354: C20th American Lit. Scott Sanders teaching, Fall 1977 (Box 1)
  - Recovery of Vision Honors H400, Fall 1977 (Box 1)
  - W103 Intro. to Creative Writing, Spring 1978 (Box 1)
  - W103, Fall 1979 (Box 1)
  - W612 Writing Fiction II, Spring 1980 (Box 1)
  - L230 Science Fiction, Fall 1980 (Box 1)
  - W612 Fiction Workshop II, Spring 1981 (Box 1)
  - L230 Science fiction, Fall 1981 (Box 1)
  - W680 Theory & Craft of Writing Writers on Writing, Spring 1982 (Box 1)
  - L230 Science fiction, Fall 1982 (Box 1)
  - H101 Ideas & human experience, Fall 1982 (Box 1)
  - W612 Writing fiction, Spring 1983 (Box 1)
  - W103 Intro. to creative writing, Fall 1984 (Box 1)
  - W554: Teaching creative writing, Fall 1984 (Box 1)
  - W612 Fiction writing workshop, Spring 1985 (Box 1)
  - L354 American Lit since 1914, Spring 1985 (Box 1)
  - W611 Fiction workshop, Fall 1985 (Box 1)
  - L208 Imagining Nature, Fall 1985 (Box 1)
  - H102, Spring 1986 (Box 1)
  - W611 Writing Fiction, Fall 1987 (Box 1)
  - L208 Imagining Nature, Fall 1987 (Box 1)
  - H102 Ideas & human experience, Spring 1988 (Box 1)
  - L204 Introduction to fiction, Spring 1988 (Box 1)
  - L208 Imagining nature, Fall 1988 (Box 1)
  - L204 Introduction to fiction, Fall 1988 (Box 1)
  - H102 Ideas and human experience, Spring 1989 (Box 1)
  - W612 Fiction workshop, Spring 1989 (Box 1)
  - W103 Introductory creative writing, Fall 1989 (Box 1)
  - W554 Teaching creative writing, Fall 1989 (Box 1)
  - W611 Graduate fiction workshop, Fall 1989 (Box 1)
  - L208 Imagining nature, Spring 1990 (Box 1)
  - Intensive freshman seminar Imagining nature, August 1990 (Box 1)
  - H102 Ideas & human experience, Spring 1991 (Box 1)
  - IFS Imagining Nature, August 1991 (Box 1)
  - L142, Spring 1992 (Box 1)
  - L142 Discussion, Spring 1992 (Box 1)
  - H102, Spring 1992 (Box 1)
  - IFS Imagining Nature, August 1992 (Box 1)
  - L141 Seeing through another's eyes, Fall 1993 (Box 2)
  - W615 Creative Nonfiction, Fall 1993 (Box 2)
  - L208 Imagining Nature, Spring 1994 (Box 2)
  - Wells H102 Section #1006 T-R 4-5:15 BH222, Spring 1994 (Box 2)
  - L141 #2551 M-W 1:25-2:15 BH310, Fall 1994 (Box 2)
  - L141 Lectures, Fall 1994 (Box 2)
  - W611 #2676, Fall 1994 (Box 2)
  - L208 Imagining Nature #2613, Spring 1995 (Box 2)
  - H201 Wells #1012, Spring 1995 (Box 2)
  - H201 II, Spring 1995 (Box 2)
  - L381 section #2661 BH142, Fall 1995 (Box 2)
  - W615 section #2684 BH235, Fall 1995 (Box 2)
  - H204 Wells section #1008, Spring 1996 (Box 2)
  - L204 BH148 section #2693, Spring 1996 (Box 2)
  - London teaching file, Summer 1996 (Box 2)
  - H204, Spring 1997 (Box 2)
  - H204 Wells, Fall 1997 (Box 2)
  - H400 Wells Seniors, Spring 1998 (Box 2)
  - H204 Wells, Fall 1998 (Box 2)
  - H400 Wells Seniors, Spring 1999 (Box 2)
  - W612, Spring 1999 (Box 2)
  - H204, Fall 1999 (Box 2)
  - W615, Spring 2000 (Box 2)
  - H204, Fall 2000 (Box 2)
  - W615, Spring 2001 (Box 2)
  - H204 section #0015, Fall 2001 (Box 2)
  - H204, Fall 2002 (Box 2)
  - H203: Life stories Wells S.P., Spring 2004 (Box 2)
  - L381 Contemp essay, Fall 2004 (Box 2)
  - W615 #24965, Fall 2004 (Box 2)
  - W311, Spring 2005 (Box 2)
  - L240 Fate of Earth section #24758, Spring 2005 (Box 2)
  - L240 Fate of Earth #21408 1-2:15 TR BH237, Spring 2006 (Box 2)
  - W615 #24477 2:30-3:30 T Bus 427, Spring 2006 (Box 2)
  - W311 #26005 TR 4-5:15 Woodburn 118, Fall 2006 (Box 2)
  - W664 #16758 Tues 6:30-9:00 Kirkwood 200, Fall 2006 (Box 2)
  - W103 9982 code 24965 M 12:20-1:10 Chem 033, 2007 (Box 3)
  - W103 Lectures/Handouts, Spring 2007 (Box 3)
  - L381 #25328, Spring 2007 (Box 3)
  - L381 (25929), Fall 2007 (Box 3)
  - W381 #25930, Fall 2007 (Box 3)
  - H400 #8207 4:00-5:30 M, Spring 2008 (Box 3)
  - W615 #25296, Spring 2008 (Box 3)
  - W615: Nonfiction workshop section 14395, Spring 2009 (Box 3)
  - L360: American life stories section 26255, Spring 2009 (Box 3)
- Faculty files, 1971-2009 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Award, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Summary Reports, 1971-2007 (Box 3)
  - Material for Faculty File, 1971-1988 (Box 3)
  - Faculty File (Box 3)
    - 1989-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994 (Box 3)
    - 1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996 (Box 3)
    - 1997 (Box 3)
    - 1998-2001 (Box 3)
    - 2002 (Box 3)
    - 2003-2005 (Box 3)
    - 2006-2009 (Box 3)
  - Restricted files (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    (RESTRICTED)
  - Restricted files (Box 4)